Guide to the Pamela Sporn Papers TAM.708
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Pamela Sporn Papers
1990-2015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sporn, Pamela
TAM.708
.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
832 Gigabytes in 584 computer files
2 videocassettes (dvcam)
2 videodisc (dvd)
29 videocassettes (minidv)
Pamela Sporn is a documentary filmmaker whose films combine personal narratives and archival materials to tell stories about working-class life. The Pamela Sporn papers contain videos and research materials related to Sporn's documentaries. The bulk of the collection and consists of approximately 400 digital video files as well as research files created by Sporn for her film A Humble Giant: 70 Years Defending Immigrants and Radicals, about immigration lawyer Ira Gollobin. It also includes DVDs of Sporn's documentaries With a Stroke of the Chevata and Disobeying Orders: GI Resistance to the Vietnam War, and analog video footage of interviews from With a Stroke of the Chevata and A Humble Giant.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Pamela Sporn in April 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.023.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series: Series I. A Humble Giant media; Series II. A Humble Giant research and production files; Series III: Other projects. Files within each series are arranged alphabetically.
Biographical Note
Pamela Sporn is a documentary filmmaker whose films combine personal narratives and archival materials to tell stories about working-class life. Sporn was the daughter of labor activists, leftist scholars, and American Communists. In 1964 her father Paul Sporn gained national attention after he was subpoenaed by the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC), and was represented by Ira Gollobin who later inspired Pamela Sporn's work as a documentarian. Sporn's documentaries generally focus on political resistance and the working class. She has produced several documentaries through her production company Grito Productions, including Disobeying Orders: G. I. Resistance to The Vietnam War (1990); Remembering the Mamoncillo (2007), about Afro-Cuban culture in New York City; With a Stroke of the Chaveta (2007), about Cuban cigar factory workers; Detroit 48202: Conversations Along a Postal Route (2017); and A Humble Giant: Seventy Years Defending Immigrants and Radicals (still in production at the time of donation), about immigration lawyer and activist Ira Gollobin.
Scope and Contents
The Pamela Sporn Papers consist of videos and research materials used by Pamela Sporn in her documentary films. The bulk of the collection consists of approximately 400 digital video files created by Sporn for her film A Humble Giant: 70 Years Defending Immigrants and Radicals, about immigration lawyer Ira Gollobin. These files include interviews and background footage from the documentary, which have been arranged by Sporn by individual and topic. There is also video footage from Ira Gollobin's 2008 memorial service and a 2005 National Lawyers Guild dinner. The collection also includes research files, budgets, fundraising, and promotional materials related to the production of the documentary. In addition to the digital video files, there are DVCAM and MiniDV cassettes that contain additional interviews.
The collection also contains DVDs of Sporn's documentaries With a Stroke of the Chaveta and Disobeying Orders: GI Resistance to the Vietnam War, both of which were produced by her small production company Grito Productions. The collection also includes MiniDV video cassettes of interviews Sporn conducted while producing With a Stroke of Chaveta, which documents the experiences of workers in Cuban cigar factories.
Other materials included in this collection consist of photocopies related to the website Unfriendly Witness: Standing Up to HUAC, which Sporn created to document her family's experience with the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC).
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Related Materials
For more information about Ira Gollobin please see the Ira Gollobin Papers (TAM 278) and the Records of the American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born (TAM 086), both held by New York University Special Collections. There is also a collection of Ira Gollobin's papers at the New York Public Library Archives and Manuscripts (MssCol 6133).
Documentary films -- United States.; Emigration and immigration law -- United States.; Foreign workers -- United States; Lawyers -- Political activity -- United States.; Working class -- History -- 20th century; Gollobin, Ira, 1911-
- Series I: A Humble Giant media, 2004-2011; 2 videocassettes (dvcam); 23 videocassettes (minidv); 831 Gigabytes in 415 computer files
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains video footage of interviews and events Pamela Sporn filmed for the documentary A Humble Giant about immigration attorney Ira Gollobin. Sporn interviewed Gollobin, his wife Ruth Gollobin, and some of his former clients and affiliates including Henry Foner, Bertell Ollman, Albert Socolov, and Sporn's father Paul Sporn. Topics covered include Gollobin's work with people who were targeted by the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC), immigrant rights activism, the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and the Spanish Civil War, and issues regarding the Labor movement and Leftist politics. Sporn also filmed much of Gollobin's memorial service which followed his death in 2008.
  The video in this series was filmed digitally. In addition to video files that were stored on a harddrive there are also DVCAM and MiniDV cassettes.
  - Albert Socolov on Ira Gollobin and the National Lawyers Guild, November 2010-May 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_1)
  - Bertell Ollman, July 14, 2007 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_2)
  - Bishop Guy Sansaricq, November 2010 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_3)
  - Claire Hirsch, March 14, 2009 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0020-708.0021)
  - Eddie Lemansky, October-November 2010 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_4)
  - Fran Goldin on Ira Gollobin, March 7, 2009; April 24, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_5, Box 1, Minidv 708.0017)
  - Henry Foner on Ira Gollobin, April 15, 2009; September 26, 2009 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_6, Box 1, Minidv 708.0013-708.0016)
  - Ira Gollobin interviews, July 23, 2007; April 19, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_7, Box 1, Minidv 708.0003-708.0004)
  - Ira Gollobin Interview: Case of Paul Sporn-HUAC Hearing 1964, May 27, 2004 (Box 1, Dvcam 708.0001-708.0002)
  - Ira Gollobin: American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born, September 8, 2007 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0006)
  - Ira Gollobin memorial service, July 19, 2008 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_8, Box 1, Minidv 708.0009-708.0012)
  - Ira Kurzban, April 19, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_9)
  - Jocelyn McCalla, October 2010-April 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_10)
  - Levi Laub, July 15, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_11)
  - Matti Mattson on Ira Gollobin and the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, April 25, 2009; April 24, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_12, Box 1, Minidv 708.0018-708.0019)
  - May Day, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_13)
  - National Lawyer's Guild Dinner, 2005 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_14, Box 1, Minidv 708.0025-708.0026)
  - Paul Sporn, April 24, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_15)
  - Ralph Shapiro, December 11, 2009 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0007-708.0008)
  - Rulx Jean-Bart, April 19, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_16)
  - Ruth Gollobin, September 7, 2008; April 20, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_17, Box 1, Minidv 708.0022-708.0024)
- Series II: A Humble Giant research and production files, 2007-2015; 431.5 Megabytes in 169 computer files.
  This series includes documents created in the process of planning the production of A Humble Giant and documents Sporn gathered while doing background research about Ira Gollobin. Planning documents include budgets, project descriptions, fundraising materials, production stills, and interview questions. Research files include both materials related directly to Ira Gollobin and materials related to his interests and areas of expertise such as immigration law, the House Un-American Activities Committee, Haiti, and the Spanish Civil War.
  - 1963 Student trip to Cuba, May 17, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_18)
  - A Humble Giant Wordpress site, 2010-2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_19)
  - American Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born, 2009-2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_20)
  - Archival footage, January 30, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_21)
  - Articles about Ira Gollobin, 2008-2015 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_22)
  - Broken Justice Report on Immigration Detainees, June 30, 2009 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_23)
  - Budgets, 2009-2012 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_24)
  - Ellis Island, 2010-2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_25)
  - Fundraising, 2009-2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_26)
  - Gollobin Memorial remarks, July 6, 2008 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_27)
  - Haiti, February 7, 2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_28)
  - House Un-American Activities Committee, 2004-2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_29)
  - Images, 2009-2012 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_30)
  - Immigration articles, 2009-2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_31)
  - Interviews, 2008-2011 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_32)
  - Ira Gollobin Papers finding aid, July 7, 2008 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_33)
  - Lincoln articles, 2009 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_34)
  - Notes on resources in the Tamiment Library, July 31, 2009 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_35)
  - Production planning, 2009 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_36)
  - Production stills, 2010 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_37)
  - Spanish Civil War, 2007-2010 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_38)
  - Synopses, 2008-2009 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_708_ER_39)
- Series III: Other projects, 1990-2007; 2 videodiscs (dvd); 6 videocassettes (minidv)
  This series contains copies of and footage from Pamela Sporn's films Disobeying Orders: G. I. Resistance to The Vietnam War and With a Stroke of the Chaveta. There is also a printed copy of Sporn's website titled "Unfriendly Witness: Standing Up to HUAC" which documented her family's experience with the House Un-American Activities Committee.
  - Con el toque de la chaveta footage, undated (Box 1, Minidv 708.0027-708.0032)
  - Con el toque de la chaveta/With a Stroke of the Chaveta, 2007 (Box 1, Dvd TW_TAM_708_0002)
  - Disobeying Orders: GI Resistance to the Vietnam War, 1990 (Box 1, Dvd TW_TAM_708_0001)
  - Unfriendly Witness: Standing Up to HUAC, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 18)